{
  "reference_number": "12073",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I think the 2050 target is too far in the future: we are already having extremely heavy rain storms, wind and drought as the result of\n climate change resulting in landslips, floods, forest and bush fires, power outages and millions of dollars worth of damage to land,\n\n housing and business. Sea level rise will make things much worse. We need to act NOW. Bring the target date forward to 2030 or\n sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The short lived gas methane is the most damaging to the environment so needs to be reduced to a sustainable level starting now.\n Methane, even with its short life, currently contributes a third of our warming emissions, and it must come down, fast, along with all\n other gases. There needs to be research on what is a sustainable level, and means to attain this level worked out. Once they are set\n\n there should be support for farmers and others to help them attain these levels, regulations set up and enforced to ensure\n sustainable levels are established in our farming culture. We are running out of time. We can't afford a vague belief that says people\n will do the right thing voluntarily or to indulge in a \"she'll be right attitude\" any more. We also need to take into account the amount of\n\n methane being released into the atmosphere through the melting of the permafrost, The only way to stop this future catastrophe is\n by slowing the warming now."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "I am really worried that we are taking things too lightly. I think we have to get into a :fighting a war\" mentality. We have to admit that our\n way of life needs to change dramatically and we will all have to make some changes to our lifestyles. We can't afford the ideas and\n dreams of an ever expanding economy. Farmers need to look at ways to reduce methane and nitrous oxide release. They need to\n\n reduce the size of their herd and use farm management systems (reduce fertiliser use, change the diet) that are truly sustainable.\n Industry needs to reduce methane leaks from gas and oil wells to zero We need to keep coal, oil,and gas in the ground Government\n\n support for clean energy heating in all schools, hospitals, public buildings, and to get them and industry like Fonterra's milk treatment\n plants off coal and fossil fuels. We need action on reducing transport emissions through efficiency standards, support for sustainable\n electric public and private transport, reducing speed limits, get away from the idea of public transport for private profit and make sure\n\n it is a publically owned service that works for the climate, the users and the workers. Encourage everybody to take action in reducing\n their own transport emissions, eg awareness of true cost of air miles in food provision Plant heaps and heaps of trees on every piece\n of spare land. Encourage private tree planting through rates rebates. Set up publicity campaigns about the importance of preserving\n\n and planting trees for short term use and long term sustainability Research and communicate the results to public on the best sort of\n trees for different uses and regions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We should NOT be able to push the target back, based on economic reasons as it would cause too much uncertainty, but we should\n\n be able to bring the emissions target forward if new evidence of what is a safe target is produced. When science says things are\n really urgent, we need to take notice of this."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No - emissions budgets should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines their long-term certainty.\n\nHowever, the ability to revise budgets in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements should be\npermitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the 350.orgs summary that supports the Government and the Climate Commission taking the following factors into\nconsideration when advising on and setting budgets: Scientific knowledge regarding climate change (his is the most important\n\nfactor) Technology relevant to climate change Economic circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy\nconsidered in its broadest sense, not just the current free-market or financial system. Social justice and the need for a fair and just\n\ntransition to a low carbon economy, so that people on low incomes are not disadvantaged by the changes. Fiscal circumstances and\nthe likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing, with consideration of the long-term goal of moving\n\nto an economy that is sustainable within resource and environmental constraints and that is not based on the assumption of\ncontinual and destructive ‘economic growth. Energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy supplies and the carbon and\n\nenergy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And keep to the time frame!"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\n\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. They should include consideration of: The real urgency of the current climate crisis\nThe need to include all aspects of society and the economy, including comprehensive education and publicity campaigns in all\nlanguages,that encourage people to feel that they are part of the solution as well as being part of the problem. The urgent need to\n\nmove away from the ‘endless growth’ model for the economy and to support economic and social structures that are environmentally\nsustainable for future generations, as well as fair and equitable so that all citizens will support it."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The CC Commission should be an independent non-partisan body that supports and undertakes research and gives advice but does\nnot make the final decisions. Communication with Parliament and the public needs to be there at all times It needs to have enough\n\nclout to be taken seriously by Government."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Again quoting from 350.org response..... I support the introduction of a carbon tax rather than maintenance of the current NZ ETS\nand would hope that the Commission will recommend the most effective form of such a tax. Whatever mechanism is chosen to put a\n\nprice on carbon, I support the Commission making recommendations for this mechanism but the implementation of such a\nmechanism should be the responsibility of the Government."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Commissionerss should have expertise in the following fields: Climate change policy (including carbon tax/emissions trading)\nResource economics and impacts (including social impacts, impact on socio-economic equity and ways of achieving a fair and just\n\ntransition Te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori interests Knowledge and awareness of our Pacific Island\nneighbours needs Climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori Experience with addressing adaptation challenges\n\nlike planning, insurance and local government Risk management Engineering and/or infrastructure Community engagement and\ncommunications. Business competitiveness Knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As I mention in my answer to question 1 I am very concerned about the effects of climate change already being experienced by New\nZealanders and our Pacific island neighbours. Having lived through the devastation of the Canterbury earthquakes and the problems\n\nwith insurance that have and still are, causing misery for many people, I can see that we need to think of the huge cost in the future\nof doing nothing or not enough now"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but feel it is important that local authorities and community and sector groups have a say\nin how this is done: a national climate change risk assessment a national adaptation plan, that supports local government. regular\n\nreview of progress towards implementing the national adaptation plan regular and ongoing communication with the public on risk and\nthe management of risk an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "regular and ongoing communication with the public on risk and the management of risk an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Be Brave!"
    }
  ]
}
